Welcome. This is a quick tour of Acme, a
text editor created by Rob Pike...
almost 20 years ago as part of Plan 9.
Although Rob created Acme on Plan 9,
Acme is now available on FreeBSD, Linux,
OS X and other Unix systems as part of
Plan 9 from User Space.
There is also a port of Acme to the
Inferno operating system which gives...
it a way to running on Windows.
The video description has a link to a
page which points to downloads and...
more information.
For me, the distinguishing feature of
Acme is it works well alongside the...
surrounding system instead of trying to
be a complete environment all by itself.
Acme does not enjoy nearly the
popularity of editors like Emacs and...
VI do,
but it has a small dedicated following.
When I had to switch to using Unix
workstations again in the early 2000's,
I missed Acme so much that I ported all
Plan 9 user programs to Unix to get...
it back.
Acme creates an experience where text is
a dynamic thing and you can execute it,
and assign it arbitrary meanings.
where plugin written in any language at
all can interact with Acme to control
windows.
The result is that you can keep using
the tools you have instead of having...
to learn the whole new system.
But you can still custom them to fit well into Acme.
In this screencast I am going to try to
convey a few of what it is like to...
use Acme.
I am going to start with the basics and
build up to a short programming session...
at the end.
One final note before the content, I
sized the video to fit Youtube...
large playing video mode exactly.
If the screen text look fuzzy, please
switch to that mode.
Because Acme was designed as part of
Plan 9,
it is a graphical program not cursor
addressed and makes extensive use of
the mouse.
This screen you are looking at is a
small Acme screen.
Its size fits exactly to Youtube 854 by
480 video box.
Normally you use a larger display.
I'd like to to use fullscreen as you see in the video.
On a laptop I foot back and forth between Acme and conventional desktop.
When I work I use two monitors, where Acme on one, and everything else on the other.
Acme takes care of window layout for you.
It automatically choosing location for each window and arrange them into columns.
In this tour, Acme has just two columns.
On larger screens, it can comfortablly supports 3 or 4.
Each column contains some number of windows.
On the screen right now, the left window contains the single window showing the quick UI tour.
And the right column contains two windows
showing a directory and a shell session.
Each window has two parts.
The top line or tag set on light blue background
shows the filename and some commands such as Del and Snarf.
The body, set on light yellow background shows the window content.
Each tag has a nearly square layout box to the left of the tag.
The layout box fills with dark blue when a window has editting that indicates you might want to save it.
Each column also has a  tag
with useful commands and layout box at the tone.
Because Acme was created on Plan 9,
its UI assumes that you have a three-button mouse and a graphical display.
There is no text-only mode or cursor addressing.
Since you cannot watch my hand using the mouse on the screencast,